拜拜
Bye-bye.
我在米雪餐厅订好位子了
I just got us reservations at Michelle's...
还可以去看《音乐人》
...and tickets to The Music Man to celebrate...
订晕之后的第一个假期
...our first holiday season as a betrothed couple.
-"订婚"  -订婚之后
- "Betrothed." - Betrothed couple.
-嗨  -你好
- Hey! - Hi!
菲比
Pheebs?
头骨
Skull?
是我妈妈的
Yeah, it's my mom's.
天啊
Oh, my God!
不是说是我妈妈的头骨
No, no, no. It's not my mom.
是我妈妈拥有的头骨
It belonged to my mom.
她以前每次圣诞节都会拿出来
She used to put it out every Christmas...
用来提醒我们
...to remind us that
就算是圣诞节  人也都会死的
even though it's Christmas, people still die.
可以放糖果在里面
And you can put candy in it.
-嘿  -嘿
- Hey. - Hey.
甘草糖
Licorice?
好啊
Sure.
-本今年和我一起过节  -太好了
- I get Ben for the holidays this year. - That's great!
-你要扮成圣诞老公公吗  -不
- Are you gonna dress up as Santa? - Nope.
我知道苏珊每年都这么做
I mean, I know Susan does every year...
可是今年我想让他了解油灯节
...but I want to take this year to teach him about Hanukkah.
也许我能教给本
And maybe I could teach Ben...
圣诞节头骨和人怎么死的
...about the Christmas skull and how people die.
你可以在今年教班认识菲比
You may need to use this year to teach Ben about Phoebe.
嗨
Hey.
-你知道他在里面吗  -不知道
- Did you know he was in there? - No.
-我们回来多久了  -大概半小时
- How long have we been home? - About half an hour.
挺好
Lovely.
你知道我刚在想什么吗
You know what I was thinking?
我们结婚之后  你会要
When we get married, are you gonna...
改随夫姓吗  姓"宾"
...change your last name to "Bing"?
不要
No.
为什么不
Why not?
姓"宾很奇怪"
"Bing" is weird.
伙计们
Oh, hey, you guys.
猜猜发生了什么  我房东刚来电话了
Guess what. My landlord just called.
我的公寓很快就可以住了
My apartment's gonna be ready soon.
我很快就要搬出去了
So I guess I'll be moving out.
菲比  我会想你的
Phoebe, I'm gonna miss you.
你会很悲伤的
Yes, you will be very sad.
我要告诉瑞秋这个好消息
I gotta go tell Rachel the good news.
你们要再一起住
You guys are gonna live together again?
-对啊  怎么了  -她和乔伊住得很开心
- Yeah, why not? - She's just having so much fun with Joey...
我以为她还会继续和他住在一起
...I just assumed she'd still be living with him.
你怎么会觉得她和乔伊住得很开心
Why do you think she's having so much fun living with Joey?
没什么  除了她
No reason, except she...
这么和我说过
...told me.
真的  她说她不要和我住
Really? She said she didn't want to live with me?
没有  她没有这么说
No. No, she didn't say that.
你该和莫妮卡聊聊了
I think you should talk to Monica now.
菲比  别担心  我确定她想和你住的
Phoebe, don't worry. I'm sure she wants to live with you.
你确定  你很肯定
You're sure? You're absolutely sure?
不  我打赌她大概会
No, but I'll bet she probably does.
大概会
Oh, probably?
我可不喜欢这个词
I don't like that word.
我知道"大概"什么意思  对
I know what "Probably" really means. Yeah, yeah.
"你妈大概不会自杀"
"Oh, your mom probably won't kill herself."
我很抱歉  但我不会把所有希望
I'm sorry, but I'm not hanging all my hopes...
都寄于瑞秋"大概"会想和我住上
...of Rachel and I living together on "Probably."
你得自己照顾自己
You gotta take care of yourself in this world.
历史教训完全没用
History teaches us nothing.
"宾"现在就那么怪了吧
"Bing" doesn't seem so weird now, does it?
太好了  你在家
Great, you're home.
猜猜菲比送我什么圣诞礼物
Guess what Phoebe got me for Christmas.
-鼓  -不  鼓啊
- Drums? - No, drums!
请给我们两个墨西哥卷外带
Hi, could we get two burritos to go, please?
抱歉  但是我没那么抱歉
I'm sorry. But not that sorry,
因为你不用和他生活
because you don't have to live with it.
钱德勒·宾有订位
We have a reservation under the name Chandler Bing.
你需要等45分钟
Okay, we'll have a table for you in about 45 minutes.
45分钟  我们8点要看《音乐人》
Forty-five minutes? We have tickets to The Music Man at 8.
抱歉  圣诞节期间是忙季  先生
I'm sorry. Christmas is a very busy time, sir.
这是因为墨西哥卷的玩笑吗
Is this because of the burrito thing?
--你得给他钱  -给钱  我就开了个玩笑
- You need to give him money. - Give him money? It was a joke!
不  这种地方都得要这样才能有桌子坐
No. To get a table. Places like this are always shaking you down.
-每个人都想贿赂他  -镇定
- Everybody wants a payoff. - All right, calm down, O'Malley.
我会给他钱的
I'll slip him some money.
不着痕迹啊
But you've got to be smooth about it.
我可以不着痕迹
Hey, I can be smooth.
我们有点急  如果你能帮我们找张桌子
We're in a bit of a hurry, so if you could get us a table...
如果能快点的话  我会很感激你的
...A little quicker, I'd appreciate it.
-当然先生  -好
- Of course, sir. - Okay.
-怎么样  -把钱放错手了
- How'd it go? - Had the money in the wrong hand.
你没觉得
Hey. You don't feel...
-想吐对吧  -没有
- ...like you're gonna throw up, do you? - No.
我有点想吐  所以就
Well, I do. So let's...
本  你
So, Ben, you...
你知道节日就要来了对吧
You know what holiday is coming up, don't you?
圣诞节
Christmas.
对  还有其他节日呢
Yeah, and you know what other holiday is coming up?
平安夜
Christmas Eve.
对  还有
Yes, but also...
油灯节
Hanukkah!
你有犹太血统  而油灯节是犹太节日
See, you're part Jewish, and Hanukkah is a Jewish holiday.
圣诞老公公有会飞的麋鹿
Santa has reindeers that can fly.
对  但油灯节
Right, but on Hanukkah...
油灯节是庆祝奇迹的节日
Hanukkah is a celebration of a miracle.
很多年之前
See, years and years ago,
很多年前有一群人叫做玛加伯人
there were these people called the Maccabees.
好  唱得很好  对
Okay, that's right. Yes...
但是油灯节我们都唱
...but on Hanukkah, we sing:
好吧  我又不是比赛
Okay, it's not a contest.
圣诞老人什么来
When is Santa coming?
不如今年  我们不要圣诞老人
How about this year, instead of Santa...
我们好好庆祝油灯节
...we have fun celebrating Hanukkah?
没圣诞老人
No Santa?
我是坏孩子吗
Was I bad?
不  你没有不乖 你今年很乖  本
No. Oh, no, no. Hey, you weren't bad. You've been very good, Ben.
-圣诞老公公生我的气  -才没有
- Santa's mad at me. - No, hey, hey, come on.
本  圣诞老人没生你的气
Ben, Santa is not mad at you, okay?
你是他最喜欢的小孩
You're his favorite little guy.
圣诞老公公会来啦
So Santa's coming?
对
Yes!
圣诞老公公会来
Santa's coming.
很简单  随意点
It's easy. Just keep it casual.
赞他两句  握手然后给他点钱
Give him a kind word, shake his hand and give him the money.
-你怎么知道这么多  -我不知道
- How do you know so much about this? - I don't know.
理查德就这么做  是吧
Richard used to do it, didn't he?
我们本来都应该开始喝汤了
We'd be eating our soup right now.
小胡子混蛋
Mustached bastard.
这些人刚走
Okay, those people just left.
快  给他钱  抢张桌子
Come on. Quick, give him the money. Get the table.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
我们赶时间  可不可以
We're in a bit of a hurry. Can we...?
所以你喜欢鼓
So you like the drums.
太棒了
That's great.
我还担心鼓会让你的
You know, I was worried that they would create maybe...
生存环境变得无法忍受
...an unbearable living situation.
但是显然没有  太好了
But, okay, well, apparently not. So, yay!
菲比  我们学了首歌了
Hey, Pheebs, we already learned a song. Check this out.
准备  一二三四
Ready? One, two, three, four.
龙舌兰
Tequila!
真有趣
That's fun.
给你们的
Here you go.
谢谢  甘瑟  放桌上吧
Thank you, Gunther. Put her there.
用硬币绝对没让这事容易点
Definitely not easier with coins.
-谢谢  -谢谢
- Thank you. - Thank you.
-谢谢  菲比  -谢谢
- Hey, Pheebs. - Hey.
给  我现在只欠你49块5了
Here. Now I only owe you 49.50.
菲比
Hey, Pheebs...
如果你想送乔伊一份
...if you want to get Joey a Christmas present
惊扰四邻的圣诞礼物
that disrupts the entire building...
为什么不给他买更微妙一点的礼物呢
...why not get him something more subtle...
比如落锤粉碎机之类的
...like a wrecking ball...
或是可以再走廊上散播的天花病毒
...or a vial of smallpox to release in the hallway?
不只是鼓的声音  每5分钟
It's not just the drum noise. Every five minutes...
乔伊把鼓棒丢到空中
...Joey throws his sticks in the air...
然后我就会听到"我的眼睛  我的眼睛"
...and I have to hear: "Oh, my eye! Oh, God, my eye!"
-烦死人了  -谢谢你
- I mean, it is so annoying. - Yes, thank you.
你看  这才是
You see, this is
普通人对于鼓的反应好吗
how normal people are supposed to react to drums.
菲比  你送乔伊鼓是为了烦瑞秋
Phoebe, you got Joey drums to annoy Rachel...
让她不想和乔伊住
...so she wouldn't want to live there anymore?
有一点吧
Maybe on some level.
乔伊  你知道
Joey, you know that
你知道你不用丢鼓棒的
you could just not throw the sticks up in the air.
不扔怎么能算是摇滚乐呢
What is rock 'r roll about that?
乔伊  送你另一个礼物
Hey, Joey, I got you another present.
等一下   先不要告诉我是什么
Hold it! Before you tell me what it is...
是什么
Okay, what is it?
是
It's a...
毒蜘蛛
...tarantula!
瑞秋  抱歉  我在想什么
God, Rachel, I'm sorry. What was I thinking...
送乔伊这么一个恶心可怕的蜘蛛
...giving Joey this big, gross, scary spider...
还用这么松的笼子
...in such a poorly constructed cage?
你在说什么 我喜欢蜘蛛
What are you talking about? I love them.
我小时候就有一只
I had a tarantula when I was a kid.
后来我的猫咪吃掉了它
But it died because my cat ate it.
之后我的猫也死了
And then my cat died.
乔伊  这不是很酷吗
But, Joey, isn't this cool?
它在我身上吗  我觉得它在我身上
Is it on me? I feel like it's on me. I got...
不是很可爱吗
Oh, isn't that adorable?
乔伊怕蜘蛛
Joey is afraid of the tarantula.
他真可爱
He's so adorable.
天啊  他太有意思了
God, he's just so much fun.
乔伊最好了  我很高兴你在这住得开心
Joey's the best. I'm glad you're having so much fun here.
慢着
Wait a minute.
怎么了
What's the matter?
我们公寓可以住了
Our apartment is ready.
那你为什么会生气呢
And that makes you angry because...?
因为你更喜欢和乔伊住
Because you'd rather live here with Joey.
-你怎么会这么想  -莫妮卡和钱德勒
- Where did you get that? - Monica and Chandler...
说你在这里很开心
...said that you were having so much fun here...
很明显架子鼓
...and apparently no amount of drums
和毒蜘蛛也不会改变你的想法
or tarantula is gonna change that.
菲比  你送乔伊这些东西
Phoebe, did you get all this stuff for Joey...
是让我不想住在这里
...to try and drive me out of the apartment?
你还不如送他一条鱼
You might as well have just gotten him a fish.
你知道我有多怕鱼
You know how fish freak me out.
鱼
Fish.
其实无所谓啦  我们要一起住得啊
But it wouldn't have mattered. You and I are gonna live together.
我们是室友  讲好的
We're roommates. That's the deal.
可是我希望你心甘情愿和我一起住
Yes, but I wanted you to want to live with me.
可是如果你在这里住得这么开心
But, okay, if you're having so much fun over here...
和你在一起更开心
It's so much more fun with you.
-我们确实很开心对吧  -对啊
- We did have fun, didn't we - We had so much fun.
他们说如果我们想  今晚可以去看
Well, anyway, they say, if we want, we could see it tonight.
-好啊  -好  好
- I would love to. - Yay, okay!
-好  好 好  -很好
- Good, good, good. - Great. All right. Good.
莫妮卡要我告诉你别敲鼓了
And Monica asked me to make the drumming stop.
好
Done.
你好  要退还那件裤子吗
Hello, sir. You here to return those pants?
不  这可是我的裤子
No, these are my pants.
好吧
Okay.
-我能帮你吗  -你这有圣诞老人装吗
- How can I help you? - Do you have a Santa outfit left?
圣诞节前2天  抱歉啊伙计
Two days before Christmas? Sorry, man.
那有节日气氛的呢
Okay, look. Do you have anything Christmas-y?
我答应了我儿子  我不想让他失望
I promised my son, and I really don't want to disappoint him.
你肯定有点什么吧
Come on, you gotta have something.
我是佳节犰狳
I'm the Holiday Armadillo!
我是圣诞老人的朋友
I'm a friend of Santa's...
他要我来祝你
...and he sent me here to wish you...
圣诞快乐
...A merry Christmas!
圣诞老公公怎么了  佳节犰狳
What happened to Santa, Holiday Armadillo?
圣诞老公公没有空
Santa was unavailable...
在这么接近圣诞节的时候
...so close to Christmas.
请进  坐吧
Come in, have a seat.
大老远从德州来  你肯定累坏了吧
You must be exhausted, coming all the way from Texas.
-德州  -对  本
- Texas? - That's right, Ben.
我是圣诞老人的
I'm Santa's representative...
南方代表
...for all the Southern states.
也是墨西哥代表
And Mexico!
但圣诞老人派我来
But Santa sent me here...
是为了给你这些礼物的  本
...to give you these presents, Ben.
这位小姐可以帮我拿下礼物的
Maybe the lady will help me with these presents.
谢谢
Wow, thanks!
不客气  本
You're welcome, Ben.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
油灯节快乐
And happy Hanukkah!
你也为油灯节而来吗  因为我有犹太血统
Are you for Hanukkah too? Because I'm part Jewish.
是吗  我也是
You are? Me too.
因为犰狳也在沙漠里晃荡吗
Because armadillos also wandered in the desert?
你想去走廊晃荡吗
You want to wander in the hall?
嗨  本
Hey, Ben!
佳节犰狳
What if the Holiday Armadillo...
和你讲讲油灯节的故事好吗
...told you all about the Festival of Lights?
好
Cool!
来吧  本
Come on, Ben.
很多年以前
Years and years ago...
有一群人  叫做
...there were these people called...
-玛加伯人   -呵  呵  呵
-...the Maccabees! - Ho, ho, ho!
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
-圣诞老人  -嗨
- Santa! - Hey!
圣诞老人  你来干嘛
What are you doing here, Santa?
我来见见我的老朋友本
Well, I'm here to see my old buddy Ben.
你来这做什么
What are you doing here...
奇怪的乌龟人
...Weird Turtle Man?
我是佳节犰狳
I'm the Holiday Armadillo...
你有着犹太血统的朋友
...your part-Jewish friend.
你派我来给本送礼物的
You sent me here to give Ben some presents.
记得吗
Remember?
什么
What?
你给我带礼物了吗  圣诞老人
Did you bring me any presents, Santa?
肯定带了啊  本
You bet I did, Ben.
放这里
Put her there.
要不是他的手太小
Well, it would have worked
应该能成功的
this time if his hands weren't so damn small.
呵呵呵
Ho, ho, ho!
本  过来继续拆礼物吧
Ben, why don't you come open more presents.
圣诞老人  佳节犰狳和我要在厨房谈一谈
Santa, the armadillo and I will have a talk in the kitchen.
我绝对想不到会说出这句话
There's a sentence I never thought I'd say.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你告诉每个人说
You called everyone and said
你找不到圣诞老人衣服
you were having trouble finding a Santa costume...
所以我向同事借了一件
...so I borrowed one from a guy at work.
谢谢  但你必须离开
Thank you, but you gotta leave.
-为什么  -因为
- Why? - Because...
我终于让他对油灯节感兴趣了
...l'm finally getting him excited about Hanukkah...
而你毁了一切
...and you're wrecking it.
可是我还没摇我的肚子呢
But I didn't get to shake my belly like a bowlful of jelly.
抱歉钱德勒  但这对我很重要
I'm sorry, Chandler, but this is really important to me.
好  我去还这件衣服
Fine, I'll give the suit back.
你可以再多借一晚吗
Hey, you think you can keep it another night?
圣诞老人  真的吗
Santa? Really?
是啊  可以吗
Yeah, is that okay?
你爸有扮过圣诞老人吗
Did your dad ever dress up like Santa?
-没有  -那就可以
- No. - Then it's okay!
本  圣诞老人要走了
Okay, Ben. Santa has to go.
和他告别
Say goodbye.
他为什么要走
No, why does he have to go?
因为圣诞老公公和佳节
Because if Santa and the Holiday...
犰狳
...Armadillo...
如果在同一个房子里太久
...are ever in the same room for too long...
宇宙会爆炸
...the universe will implode!
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
为什么不是犰狳走呢   我要圣诞老人
No, why can't the armadillo leave? I want Santa.
我放弃了  圣诞老人
Fine, I give up. Santa...
圣诞老人留下
Santa can stay!
我留下
Well, I'll stay...
但只是因为我想听听有关油灯节的故事
...but only because I want to hear about Hanukkah.
本  你愿意和圣诞老人坐在一起
Ben, will you sit here with Santa...
听听油灯节的故事吗
...and learn about Hanukkah?
好啊  圣诞老人
Okay, Santa.
-谢谢  -不客气
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
好了  现在
All right, it's time...
是讲述油灯节故事的时候了
...for the story of Hanukkah.
很多年以前
Years and years ago...
有一群人  叫做玛加伯人
...there were these people called the Maccabees!
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
看看这地方
Oh, wow, look at this place!
这太糟糕了
Oh, this is terrible.
他们做了太多改变
They've made so many changes...
我都感觉不到我祖母的存在了
...I can't even feel my grandmother's presence anymore.
新烛台
Oh, new sconces!
-天啊  -怎么了
- Oh, my God! - What?
记得你告诉我
Okay, remember how you told me
你祖母砌了一道墙
that your grandmother put up that wall...
-把这间房隔成两个卧室吗  -是吧
- ...to make that into two bedrooms? - Yeah.
之后你害怕房东会发现
And then you are afraid that the landlord might find out...
-然后把墙推倒了  -是吗
- ...and then tear it down? - Yeah?
你知道我要说什么吗
Do you really not know where I'm going with this?
墙不见了  变成一个房间了
It left. It's one huge room.
不
Oh, no!
看见了吧
See?
我们大概要把墙重新砌起来
I guess we'll just have to put the wall back up.
-不行  因为有天窗了  -还有天窗
- You can't, because of the new skylight. - There's a skylight?
我怎么办  找个其他地方住吗
So, what should we do? Should we start looking for a new place?
我能感觉到
You know, I'm sensing...
我祖母不高兴看见这些改变
...that my grandmother would not be comfortable with that.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
又能感觉到她了是吧
Starting to feel her again there, are we?
-一点点  -是吧
- A little bit. Yeah. - Yeah.
菲比  也许你祖母在说
Pheebs, is your grandmother
你应该一个人在这住
maybe saying that you should live here alone?
你也听到了  你有天赋啊
You heard it too? You have the gift.
菲比  没事的
Phoebe, it's okay.
我喜欢和乔伊住
I like living with Joey.
-你确定吗  -拜托  我讨厌打包
- Are you sure? - Please. I hate packing...
那里离公司比较近
...it's closer to work.
我们在一起很开心
And we do have fun.
虽然我真的会想念和你住在一起的日子
Although, I'm really gonna miss living with you.
-我也是  -我知道
- Oh, me too. - I know.
等一下  你有没有听到
Oh, wait. Did you hear that?
我听到你祖母说话
Listen. I'm getting something from your grandmother.
她说既然你要一个人住这里
She said that since you get to keep the one-bedroom apartment...
你该把那紫色椅子给瑞秋
...you should give Rachel the purple chair.
我没有听到
No, I do not hear that.
奇迹在于那一点点的油
And the miracle was that that little bit of oil...
应该只够烧一天的  却烧了
...that should have lasted just one day, burned for...
-整整八天  -对
- Eight whole days. - That's right.
所以我们才要庆祝油灯节  结束
And that's why we celebrate Hanukkah today. The end.
-很好  -对
- Awesome. - Yeah.
我最喜欢的部份
My favorite part...
是超人救出全埃及的犹太人
...was when Superman flew all the Jews out of Egypt.
犰狳不是那么喜欢那部份
The armadillo was actually not so thrilled about that part.
本  是时候
Okay, Ben, it's time to light...
燃起油灯节的蜡烛了
...the Hanukkah candles!
嗨
Hey.
好像是复活节兔子的葬礼
Wow! Looks like the Easter Bunny's funeral in here.
我们要点蜡烛
Come on, come on. We're lighting the candles.
我了解为什么超人在这里
I understand why Superman is here...
但为什么有豪猪参加复活节兔子的葬礼
...but why is there a porcupine at the Easter Bunny's funeral?
-你抓住它了吗  -抓住了
- Did you get it? - I got it.
它进笼子了没
Is it back in the cage?
它在笼子里了
It's back in the cage.
笼子关好了吗
Is the cage closed?
乔伊  出来好吗  别胆小怕事好吗
Joey, will you just come out here and stop being such a baby!